Brockton, Mass. First Parish Congregational Church records, 1738-1980.
Congregational Library & Archives
Brockton, Mass. First Parish Congregational Church records, 1738-1980.
RG0037
Congregational Library & Archives
1.92 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes, 1 reel)
The First Parish Congregational Church in Brockton was originally founded as the Fourth Parish Church in Bridgewater in 1737 and formally gathered as such in 1740. The name of the church changed, in 1823, to First Parish Congregational Church to reflect the incorporation of the town of North Bridgewater. In 1827 a portion of the church's membership left to form the South Congregational Church and in 1850 another portion left to form the Porter Evangelical Congregational Church. In 1874 the town of North Bridgewater changed to Brockton. In 1980 the First Parish Congregational Church merged with the South Congregational Church, the Porter Congregational Church, and the Waldo Congregational Church to form the Christ Congregational Church which continues to operate today. This collection contains the administrative, legal, fiscal, and vital records of the church and includes meeting minutes, membership records, building records, and ministerial records.
First Parish Congregational Church (Brockton, Mass.)
Fourth Parish Church (Bridgewater, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
While the records are unclear, it appears that this collection is the result of two major deposits. The first deposit, by Rev. James H. O'Brien of the First Parish Congregational Church in Brockton, occured in 1965. That same year some records were microfilmed by the Harvard University Reprographic Services (originally RG1339). In 1980, when the First Parish Congregational Church reformed into the Christ Congregational Church, additional First Parish Congregational Church materials were deposited with the Congregational Library & Archives along with materials from the South, Porter, and Waldo Congregational churches; no accession number.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Custodial History
Many of the items within the collection were damaged by a fire in 1965. In response to the damage sustained by the collection due to the fire, the First Parish Congregational Church contracted with F. C. Wiedemann for document preservation.
Historical Note
The First Parish Congregational Church in Brockton was originally founded as the Fourth Parish Church in Bridgewater in March, 1737, with the construction of the first meeting house for the community that had formed in Bridgewater's North. In 1738, the community sent a petition to the General Court of Massachusetts to designate the area as a unique parish within Bridgewater. The request was granted in December, 1739 with the formation of the North Precinct of Bridgewater. John Porter, a 1736 graduate of Harvard, was ordained as the first minister of the Fourth Parish Church in October, 1740 at the same time that the church was formally gathered.
Membership within the church grew significantly under Rev. Porter, mimicking the expansion of the community. The expansion of the parish community resulted in the need for a new meeting house; the dedication of the second meeting house, which was twice as large as the first building, was held in December, 1763. Rev. Porter was interested in education and readily helped prepare talented youth for higher education during his ministry. During the American Revolution, Rev. Porter supported the Continental Army by organizing an effort which resulted in the shipment of 5580 pounds of beef to the army. He served as the minister of the church until his death in 1802.
The first parish Sunday school was organized in 1818 with an initial enrolment of 185 students. In 1823 the North Precinct of Bridgewater as incorporated as the town of North Bridgewater. At this time, the name of the church was changed to the First Parish Congregational Church. By the 1820s the second meeting house was beginning to require extensive fixes and renovations to meet the needs of the community. Instead of embarking on those costly renovations, the community found the funds to build the third meeting house, which was dedicated in November, 1827. In 1836 a significant portion of the parish withdrew from the church due to the formation of the South Congregational Church in Plain Village (now Campello) North Bridgewater.
The ordination of Rev. Paul Couch in 1835 resulted in a liberalization of the First Parish's teachings during his 24 years of ministry. This ultimately resulted in another significant portion of the church separating in 1850 to form the Porter Evangelical Congregational Church. Rev. Couch also oversaw construction of the fourth meeting house, also known as the Old Brown Church. This building was dedicated in July, 1854. In 1874 the name of the town of North Bridgewater was changed to Brockton.
During 1897 the fifth meeting house was constructed. This stone building was dedicated in December, 1897 and Rev. Alan Hudson was installed as the minister the same day. The fifth meeting house was largely destroyed in an early morning fire on February 19, 1965. The sixth and final meeting house was constructed in 1967 with the dedication taking place in June. In 1980 the First Parish Congregational Church, South Congregational Church, Porter Congregational Church, and Waldo Congregational Church merged to form the Christ Congregational Church. The Christ Congregational Church in Brockton continues to serve the local community today. The sixth meeting house is now the house of warship for the Mt. Moriah Baptist Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative, legal, fiscal, and vital records of the First Parish Congregational Church in Brockton, Massachusetts. The collection includes the meeting minutes of the church and parish, membership records, vital statistics for church members, including baptismal and marriage records, ministerial records, building records, financial records, pew deeds, assessment results, and important legal documents.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged into the two series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged in chronological order, by start date, primarily, and by topic secondarily.
Series 1: Church and Parish records, 1738-1980
Series 2: Financial and legal records, 1764-1965
Physical Access
Some materials within the collection have been damaged by exposure to fire. There may be special handling instructions for these materials and/or limited access provided to certain damaged items.
Technical Requirements
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Related Materials
In 1980, the First Parish Congregational, South Congregational, Porter Congregational, and Waldo Congregational Churchs merged into a single entity, the Christ Congregational Church. The records of all four churches are held at the Congregational Library & Archives:
Brockton, Mass. South Congregational Church records, 1835-1979.
Brockton, Mass. Porter Congregational Church, 1800-1979.
Brockton, Mass. Waldo Congregational Church, 1896-1980.
Bibliography
Two Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Booklet. Brockton: First Parish Congregational Church, 1962. 17.11.1 B78.33 CHrCC
Baptismal records.; Church discipline.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Installation (clergy).; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Pews and pew rights.; Sermons, American -- Early works to 1800.; Sunday schools -- Records.; Bridgewater (Mass.) -- Church history.; Brockton (Mass.) -- Church history.; Christ Congregational Church (Brockton, Mass.); First Parish Congregational Church (Brockton, Mass.); Fourth Parish Church (Bridgewater, Mass.); North Bridgewater (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Church and parish records, 1738 1980; 1738-1980; 28 Files; (10 volumes, 17 folders, 1 reel)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administration of the church and parish, vital records, and well as records related to the religious operations of the church. Included in the series are church and parish record books, membership records, ministerial records, Sunday school materials, and historical sketches.
  - Parish records, 1738 1852; 1738-1852 (Box 2)
    Digital Copies
    These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This volume contains the records of the parish community. Included within the records is a copy of the petition sent to the General Court that resulted in the formation of the North Precinct in Bridgewater. Also included are meeting minutes, notifications of tax deadlines, discussion of meeting house maintenance and improvements, the installation of Rev. John Porter, financial records, and records related to the incorporation of the North Precinct into North Bridgewater.
  - Parish records, 1852 1893; 1852-1893 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Parish records, 1894 1916; 1894-1916 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - A Church Book, 1740 1805; 1740-1805 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    This volume contains the administrative records of the church and valuable membership records. Included in the volume are meeting minutes, a copy of the church covenant, baptismal records, membership records, records of admission, communion records, disciplinary records, and marriage records.
  - Church records, 1812 1874; 1812-1874 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1874 1894; 1874-1894 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Church records, 1894 1914; 1894-1914 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Church and parish records, 1914 1922; 1914-1922 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Sermon: Isaiah 60:22, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ecclesiastical council records, 1811 1915; 1811, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership records, 1817 1962; 1817-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Historical sketch and sermon, 1820 1890; 1820, 1890 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Sunday school records, 1826 1860; 1826-1860 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Installation services, 1835 1922; 1835-1922 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Historical sketch manuscript, 1847 1932; 1847, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Building dedication services, 1853 1967; 1853-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Extracts of church records, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Anniversary and memorial services, 1877 1962; 1877-1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rev. Douglas Carlile resignation letter, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Separated Materials
    This letter, and related clipping, was removed from the Parish Records, 1852-1893.
  - Society and committee reports, 1898 1912; 1898-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sunday school reports, 1898 1912; 1898-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Historical poem, circa 1905; 17 Files; (9 volumes, 7 folders, 1 reel) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alan Hudson manuscript and sermons, 1907 1914; 1907-1914, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Asa Meech research materials, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Microfilm records: Negative, 1965; 1738 1890; 1738-1890 (Reel 1)
    Location of Originals
    This microfilm is a negative copy of records originally held by the First Parish Congregational Church. The physical records on this microfilm are currently held by the Congregational Library & Archives and are a part of this collection.
    This microfilm contains copies of several record books and documents, all dating from the earliest periods of the church's history. Below is an index of the records included on the reel.
    Index of Microfilmed Records
    Church records, 1740-1832
    Historical sketch and sermon, 1820, 1890
    Quitclaim deed, 1763
    Parish records, 1738-1852
    South Congregational Society records, 1836-1845
    Plan to award certificates, 1827-1836
    Names of those who left the society, 1840-1853
    Names of those who left the parish, 1849-1852
    Salary receipts of John Porter, 1746-1754
  - A Coppying Out, 1980 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Poems and photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    This folder contains a collection of poems and photographs bound together in a sort of scrapbook. The majority of the poems are related to an adjacent photograph. The photographs are all of a single manor and people who either visited or lived there. Unfortunately, the exact location of the manor is unknown as are the identities of the people pictured.
  - Sunday school rewards of merit, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Financial and legal records, 1764 1965; 1764-1965; 20 Files; (4 volumes, 16 folders)
  This series contains the financial and legal records of the church. Included in the materials are financial ledgers, building-specific financial records, pew deeds, assessment and survey results, and legal documents.
  - Land deeds and lease, 1764 1854; 1764-1854 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1786- 1862; 1786-1862 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Committee payment, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Incorporation of North Bridgewater, 1818 1821; 1818-1821 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pew deeds and sales, 1827 1942; 1827-1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Some of the materials present in this folder were removed from the Treasurer's book, 1857-1865.
  - Treasurer's book, 1857 1865; 1857-1865 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Assessor's book, 1860 1865; 1860-1865 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Building assessment, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bill payments, 1864 1865; 1864-1865 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Final wills and testaments, 1871 1897; 1871-1897 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Building contract addendum, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1898 1947; 1898-1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Deeds and leases, 1904 1926; 1904-1926 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cash book of the Women's Group, 1904 1933; 1904-1933 (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Documents of incorporation, 1906 1914; 1906, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - James A. Roarty lawsuit documents, 1914 1917; 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Insurance letter, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Agreement with F. C. Wiedemann, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Estate assessment, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Land surveys, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)